<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>From Fish To Physician on From Fish to Physician</title>
    <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/</link>
    <description>Recent content in From Fish To Physician on From Fish to Physician</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.kidneyfish.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Oh Mg (part 2)</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why does low Mg cause low K?
 Distal Na and K transport and the transepithelial voltage  Hypomagnesaemia: easy to find if you go looking for it; usually left well alone. (And often caused by a drug.)
But sometimes hypomagnesaemia is worth paying attention to if it is contributing to another electrolyte disorder such as hypocalcaemia or hypokalaemia. It is widely recognised that Mg deficiency can cause refractory hypokalaemia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to assess free water balance in dysnatraemia</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/skinning-a-cat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/skinning-a-cat/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  How to assess free water balance in the dysnatraemias
 How to factor in solute / cation balance   “There’s more than one way to skin a cat.”
— Proverb
 So the proverb goes. But that is only because whoever came up with the proverb back in the 19th century had never attempted to assess free water balance in a case of hyponatraemia. More than any other electrolyte disorder, hyponatraemia has the capacity to become unneccessarily complicated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should I stop the furosemide?</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  What effect do loop diuretics have on renal free water clearance?
 Should we stop furosemide in hyponatraemia?
 Why do we need to restrict water intake when giving furosemide in hyponatraemia?  We are mostly water and rapidly run into trouble when we become under- or over-hydrated. We could argue, therefore, that one of the kidney’s most important jobs is that of maintaining water homeostasis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terlipressin and hyponatraemia</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/terlipressin-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/terlipressin-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  The evolution of the vasopressin system
 How can one hormone regulate two physiological parameters (tonicity and blood pressure)?
 Why does terlipressin not always cause profound hyponatraemia?   “Thousands have lived without love, not one without water.”
— WH Auden
  Does terlipressin cause hyponatraemia? We had a patient with hepatorenal syndrome on the unit recently. Her sodium was 125 mM and I found myself wondering - as I always do in such a patient - whether terlipressin could be contributing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh Mg (part 1)</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/ppis-and-magnesium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/ppis-and-magnesium/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  PPIs are associated with hypomagnesaemia
 PPIs reduce intestinal Mg2+ absorption
 diuretics, CNIs and anti-cancer agents promote renal Mg2+ loss   PPIs and Mg We had a referral recently for a case of persistent hypomagnesaemia “? cause”. As is often the case, the patient had been taking a PPI for some years. There was no obvious alternative explanation and FEMg was low - so we blamed this as the likely culprit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugar and spice and all things nice</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Electrolyte-free water clearance can help assess disorders of sodium homeostasis
 Potassium supplementation can help in cases of hyponatraemia   What are we made of?  What are little girls made of?
What are little girls made of?
Sugar and spice
And all things nice
That’s what little girls are made of
— Nursery Rhyme
 Well we are not made of sugar and spice - but what are we made of?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filtration-reabsorption: the central renal paradox</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/filtration-reabsorption-the-central-renal-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/filtration-reabsorption-the-central-renal-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  How the kidney evolved to filter first and reabsorb later
 How we came to know how the kidney works in this way   It is so obvious!  ‘One never notices what has been done; one can only see what remains to be done.’
— Marie Curie
 As facts become established dogma, it becomes almost impossible to conceive of a time when they were not known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why write a blog?</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/first-post/</guid>
      <description>“Renal physiology has now passed into a quantitative phase where unsupported speculation and empirical description are no longer warranted.”
— Homer Smith, 1951
 In this post…  What are the aims of this blog?
 Where does the name come from?   Why write a blog? I enjoy learning about renal physiology - in particular those aspects that are relevant to clinical disorders of fluid-electrolyte balance. However I have a bad habit of reading up on a topic, understanding it for 10 minutes, and promptly forgetting it again.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
