<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>water on From Fish to Physician</title>
    <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/tags/water/</link>
    <description>Recent content in water on From Fish to Physician</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.kidneyfish.net/tags/water/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The E=mc2 of nephrology</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/e-mc-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/e-mc-2/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why drinking seawater causes dehydration
 Why giving 0.9% NaCl can exacerbate hyponatraemia in some circumstances
 How much water do you have to drink to cause hyponatraemia
 Why most patients on furosemide should also have restricted water intake
 Why a “tea and toast” diet causes hyponatraemia
 Why limiting dietary solute intake can help in nephrogenic diabetes insipidus  Physicists may still be searching for the grand unified theory of everything, but nephrologists have come pretty close to a unified theory of urine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is a diuretic not a diuretic?</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/nephrogenic-di/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/nephrogenic-di/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  The paradoxical anti-diuretic effects of diuretics
 A general approach to nephrogenic diabetes insipidus   When is a tractor not a tractor?
…
When it turns into a field
  Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus As nephrologists, we are often asked for advice on how to manage patients with nephrogenic diabetes insipidus (NDI). Almost always, this has been caused by current or historic lithium exposure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should I stop the furosemide?</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  What effect do loop diuretics have on renal free water clearance?
 Should we stop furosemide in hyponatraemia?
 Why do we need to restrict water intake when giving furosemide in hyponatraemia?  We are mostly water and rapidly run into trouble when we become under- or over-hydrated. We could argue, therefore, that one of the kidney’s most important jobs is that of maintaining water homeostasis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terlipressin and hyponatraemia</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/terlipressin-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/terlipressin-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  The evolution of the vasopressin system
 How can one hormone regulate two physiological parameters (tonicity and blood pressure)?
 Why does terlipressin not always cause profound hyponatraemia?   “Thousands have lived without love, not one without water.”
— WH Auden
  Does terlipressin cause hyponatraemia? We had a patient with hepatorenal syndrome on the unit recently. Her sodium was 125 mM and I found myself wondering - as I always do in such a patient - whether terlipressin could be contributing.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
