<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>physiology on From Fish to Physician</title>
    <link>/categories/physiology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in physiology on From Fish to Physician</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/physiology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Salt reduction</title>
      <link>/post/salt-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/salt-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Summary Clinical pearls   Summary Salt reduction lowers blood pressure and prevents CVD. Ditto K supplementation. More effective at a population than an individual level. Contribution from kidney, vasculature, CNS, immune system - but primacy of pressure natriuresis and the RAAS. Salt preference because salt activates dopaminergic mesolimbic reward pathways.
 Clinical pearls  units of salt (Big Mac / packet of crisps / 500 ml 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The E=mc2 of nephrology</title>
      <link>/post/e-mc-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/e-mc-2/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why drinking seawater causes dehydration
 Why giving 0.9% NaCl can exacerbate hyponatraemia in some circumstances
 How much water do you have to drink to cause hyponatraemia
 Why most patients on furosemide should also have restricted water intake
 Why a “tea and toast” diet causes hyponatraemia
 Why limiting dietary solute intake can help in nephrogenic diabetes insipidus  Physicists may still be searching for the grand unified theory of everything, but nephrologists have come pretty close to a unified theory of urine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is a diuretic not a diuretic?</title>
      <link>/post/nephrogenic-di/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/nephrogenic-di/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  The paradoxical anti-diuretic effects of diuretics
 A general approach to nephrogenic diabetes insipidus   When is a tractor not a tractor?
…
When it turns into a field
  Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus Nephrologists are often asked for advice on how to manage patients with nephrogenic diabetes insipidus (NDI). Almost always, this has been caused by current or historic lithium exposure.
This is one of those referrals that invariably sends me scuttling back to review original literature, because I can never quite remember how on earth diuretics are supposed to magically transform into anti-diuretics in this context, nor the relative merits of thiazides / amiloride / acetazolamide.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pan-hypo-electrolytes</title>
      <link>/post/pan-hypo-electrolytes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/pan-hypo-electrolytes/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  What to do when everything is low
 Refeeding syndrome
 Acquired Bartter syndrome  One referral that is always a bit of a head-scratcher is the patient with low Na, low K, low Mg, low PO4 - what could reasonably be called pan-hypo-electrolytes. This is a pretty common scenario in hospitalised patients - and we’ll come to the differential diagnosis in a subsequent post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh Mg (part 2)</title>
      <link>/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why does low Mg cause low K?
 Distal Na and K transport and the transepithelial voltage  Hypomagnesaemia: easy to find if you go looking for it; usually left well alone. (And often caused by a drug.)
But sometimes hypomagnesaemia is worth paying attention to if it is contributing to another electrolyte disorder such as hypocalcaemia or hypokalaemia. Any medical student can tell you that Mg deficiency can cause refractory hypokalaemia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should I stop the furosemide?</title>
      <link>/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/diuretics-and-water-one/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  What effect do loop diuretics have on renal free water clearance?
 Should we stop furosemide in hyponatraemia?
 Why do we need to restrict water intake when giving furosemide in hyponatraemia?  We are mostly water and rapidly run into trouble when we become under- or over-hydrated. We could argue, therefore, that one of the kidney’s most important jobs is that of maintaining water homeostasis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terlipressin and hyponatraemia</title>
      <link>/post/terlipressin-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/terlipressin-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  The evolution of the vasopressin system
 How can one hormone regulate two physiological parameters (tonicity and blood pressure)?
 Why does terlipressin not always cause profound hyponatraemia?   “Thousands have lived without love, not one without water.”
— WH Auden
  Does terlipressin cause hyponatraemia? We had a patient with hepatorenal syndrome on the unit recently. Her sodium was 125 mM and I found myself wondering - as I always do in such a patient - whether terlipressin could be contributing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugar and spice and all things nice</title>
      <link>/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Electrolyte-free water clearance can help assess disorders of sodium homeostasis
 Potassium supplementation can help in cases of hyponatraemia   What are we made of?  What are little girls made of?
What are little girls made of?
Sugar and spice
And all things nice
That’s what little girls are made of
— Nursery Rhyme
 Well we are not made of sugar and spice - but what are we made of?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filtration-reabsorption: the central renal paradox</title>
      <link>/post/filtration-reabsorption-the-central-renal-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/filtration-reabsorption-the-central-renal-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  How the kidney evolved to filter first and reabsorb later
 How we came to know how the kidney works in this way   It is so obvious!  ‘One never notices what has been done; one can only see what remains to be done.’
— Marie Curie
 As facts become established dogma, it becomes almost impossible to conceive of a time when they were not known.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>