<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>potassium on From Fish to Physician</title>
    <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/tags/potassium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in potassium on From Fish to Physician</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.kidneyfish.net/tags/potassium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dietary salt: clinical pearls</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/salt-pearls/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/salt-pearls/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  A summary of our recent salt perspectives paper A few “clinical pearls” relating to salt   Introduction We (with Matt Bailey and Bean Dhaun) recently wrote a perspectives article on salt and disease. This was an entertaining and educational process. Here I reflect on what I learned while writing the review, giving a little more space to some potentially useful “clinical pearls”.
(As the following is discussed in detail and fully referenced in our paper, I have not inserted many references below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh Mg (part 2)</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why does low Mg cause low K?
 Distal Na and K transport and the transepithelial voltage  Hypomagnesaemia: easy to find if you go looking for it; usually left well alone. (And often caused by a drug.)
But sometimes hypomagnesaemia is worth paying attention to if it is contributing to another electrolyte disorder such as hypocalcaemia or hypokalaemia. Any medical student can tell you that Mg deficiency can cause refractory hypokalaemia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugar and spice and all things nice</title>
      <link>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.kidneyfish.net/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Electrolyte-free water clearance can help assess disorders of sodium homeostasis
 Potassium supplementation can help in cases of hyponatraemia   What are we made of?  What are little girls made of?
What are little girls made of?
Sugar and spice
And all things nice
That’s what little girls are made of
— Nursery Rhyme
 Well we are not made of sugar and spice - but what are we made of?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
