<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>potassium on From Fish to Physician</title>
    <link>/tags/potassium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in potassium on From Fish to Physician</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/potassium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Salt reduction</title>
      <link>/post/salt-reduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/salt-reduction/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Summary Clinical pearls   Summary Salt reduction lowers blood pressure and prevents CVD. Ditto K supplementation. More effective at a population than an individual level. Contribution from kidney, vasculature, CNS, immune system - but primacy of pressure natriuresis and the RAAS. Salt preference because salt activates dopaminergic mesolimbic reward pathways.
 Clinical pearls  units of salt (Big Mac / packet of crisps / 500 ml 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh Mg (part 2)</title>
      <link>/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/magnesium-and-potassium/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Why does low Mg cause low K?
 Distal Na and K transport and the transepithelial voltage  Hypomagnesaemia: easy to find if you go looking for it; usually left well alone. (And often caused by a drug.)
But sometimes hypomagnesaemia is worth paying attention to if it is contributing to another electrolyte disorder such as hypocalcaemia or hypokalaemia. Any medical student can tell you that Mg deficiency can cause refractory hypokalaemia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugar and spice and all things nice</title>
      <link>/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sugar-and-spice-and-all-things-nice/</guid>
      <description>In this post…  Electrolyte-free water clearance can help assess disorders of sodium homeostasis
 Potassium supplementation can help in cases of hyponatraemia   What are we made of?  What are little girls made of?
What are little girls made of?
Sugar and spice
And all things nice
That’s what little girls are made of
— Nursery Rhyme
 Well we are not made of sugar and spice - but what are we made of?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>